Guide to the St. Philip's Episcopal Church records, 1878-2002 RL.11847
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
St. Philip's Episcopal Church records
1878-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
St. Philip's Episcopal Church (Durham, N.C.)
RL.11847
21021 items
St. Philip's Episcopal Church was founded in 1878 in Durham, N.C. This collections contains vestry minutes, correspondence, minutes from various organizations within the church, rector's notes, church bulletins and programs, slides, photographs, financial records, appointment books, scrapbooks, clippings, canvass reports, auditor's reports, sermons, and printed materials. Also included are the records, notes, and correspondence related to parish historian Harold Parker's history of the church (published in 1997), as well as a complete file of the church's extant sermons (1912-1994) Parker compiled for another book. There are also five reels of microfilm containing copies of vestry minutes, marriage records, a church register, etc., organized by Mr. Parker into roughly chronological order and divided into sections by rectorship.
Biographical / Historical
St. Philip's Episcopal Church was founded in 1878 in Durham, N.C.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The St. Philip's Episcopal Church records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a deposit between 1993 and 2002.
Related Materials
Harold T. Parker was a professor at Duke University, and his papers are part of Duke University Archives: https://find.library.duke.edu/catalog/DUKE003078946
The Rubenstein also holds the papers of Elizabeth Roberts, who was a member of St. Philip's Episcopal Church: https://find.library.duke.edu/catalog/DUKE001801221
Other items relating to St. Philip's have been individually cataloged and can be found by searching the catalog for "St. Philip's Episcopal Church".
Collection Overview
This collections contains vestry minutes, correspondence, minutes from various organizations within the church, rector's notes, church bulletins and programs, slides, photographs, financial records, appointment books, scrapbooks, clippings, canvass reports, auditor's reports, sermons, and printed materials. Also included are the records, notes, and correspondence related to parish historian Harold Parker's history of the church (published in 1997), as well as a complete file of the church's extant sermons (1912-1994) Parker compiled for another book. There are also five reels of microfilm containing copies of vestry minutes, marriage records, a church register, etc., organized by Mr. Parker into roughly chronological order and divided into sections by rectorship.
Marriage records -- North Carolina -- Durham County; Church records and registers -- North Carolina -- Durham County; Sermons, American; Church correspondence; Clergy -- Correspondence; Durham (N.C.) -- Church history; North Carolina -- Church history; Durham County (N.C.) -- Genealogy; Photographs; Slides (photographs); Scrapbooks; Clippings (information artifacts); Microfilms; Parker, Harold Talbot, 1907-; Episcopal Church -- North Carolina; Episcopal Church. Diocese of North Carolina; Episcopal Church -- Sermons
- Accession: 1993-0206
  - Thomas E. Bollinger, several undertakings, 1969-1975 (Box 93/206: 1)
  - Bollinger: annual parish meeting, 1968-1974 (Box 93/206: 1)
  - Bollinger: trial use of proposed prayer book (Box 93/206: 1)
  - Bollinger: Lenten program, 1970-1972 (Box 93/206: 1)
  - Bollinger: self-study, 1970-1971, 1974 (Box 93/206: 1)
  - Vestry minutes, 1967 February-1968 December (Box 93/206: 1)
  - Edwards-Sherman correspondence, 1954-1959 (Box 93/206: 1)
  - Transfers, 1954-1965 (Box 93/206: 1)
  - Edwards-Sherman, misc. papers (Box 93/206: 2)
  - Yates, Haden, Edwards, Sherman correspondence (Box 93/206: 2)
  - Haden, Edwards Laymen's League, 1948-1954 (Box 93/206: 2)
  - Edwards, Sherman, ECW: board meeting minutes, minutes of general meetings, 1954-1966 (Box 93/206: 2)
  - Bollinger, 1968-1974 (Box 93/206: 2)
  - Vestry minutes with rector's notes, 1963 January-1967 January (Box 93/206: 3)
  - Vestry minutes, 1955 January-1964 December (Box 93/206: 3)
  - Epistle to the Philippians, 1952-1974 (Box 93/206: 3)
  - Sherman misc. (Box 93/206: 4)
  - Vestry minutes, 1972 June-1974 December (Box 93/206: 4)
  - Bulletins, 1968-1970, 1973-1974 (Box 93/206: 4)
  - Haden, pictures: parish house and church, 1948-1954 (Box 93/206: 4)
  - Appointment books and financial records (Box 93/206: 4)
  - Bollinger: vestry minutes, 1968 May-1972 May (Box 93/206: 5)
  - Annual parochial reports, 1935-1965 (Box 93/206: 5)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1954-1969 (Box 93/206: 5)
  - Bollinger, Canvass, 1970-1972, 1974 (Box 93/206: 5)
  - Committee minutes: building, administrative, and phase 1, 1972 (Box 93/206: 5)
  - Bulletins, 1960, 1963-1967 (Box 93/206: 6)
  - Yates, Haden, Edwards: church school, minutes of meeting of Sun School faculty, talks by Edwards and Watson, 1936-1952, 1954-1955 (Box 93/206: 6)
  - Edwards/Sherman: every member canvass results, financial papers, 1956-1969 (Box 93/206: 6)
  - Memorials, 1936-1967 (Box 93/206: 6)
  - Bollinger, vestry minutes, 1975-1976 (Box 93/206: 6)
  - Annual Congressional meeting - St. Andrews, 1960-1974 (Box 93/206: 7)
  - Transfers, 1936-1944, 1947-1953 (Box 93/206: 7)
  - Bollinger, misc., 1967-1971 (Box 93/206: 7)
  - Post-Bost register of church services, 1955 July-1972 May (Box 93/206: 7)
  - Bollinger: auditor's reports, 1966-1970 (Box 93/206: 8)
  - Bollinger: treasurer's reports, 1972-1975 (Box 93/206: 8)
  - Bollinger: Lent, 1972-1973 (Box 93/206: 8)
  - Bulletins, 1952-1956, 1958 (Box 93/206: 8)
  - Transfers, 1966-1968 (Box 93/206: 8)
  - Bollinger, misc. (Box 93/206: 8)
  - Bollinger, Canvass, 1973-1974 (Box 93/206: 8)
  - Registers 1, 2, and 3, 1878-1937 (Box 93/206: 9)
  - Old lectern Bible (Box 93/206: 9)
    Scope and Contents
    Given by S.S. Class of Calvary, Tarboro in 1881, used until 1960
  - Sherman, ECW, internal correspondence and reports, 1958-1965 (Box 93/206: 9)
  - Bollinger, vestry minutes, 1968 May-1970 June (Box 93/206: 10)
  - Haden, Sherman, Bollinger, official reports, 1945-1975 (Box 93/206: 10)
  - Sherman, misc. (Box 93/206: 10)
  - Interim period, vestry business, 1977-1978 (Box 93/206: 10)
  - Interim period, search for new rector, 1977-1978 (Box 93/206: 11)
  - Edwards, Sunday school; Sermons: Yates, Edwards, Sherman, Bollinger (Box 93/206: 11)
  - Bost misc. papers (Box 93/206: 11)
  - Edwards, Sherman, misc, 1951-1967 (Box 93/206: 11)
  - Bollinger, misc. (Box 93/206: 11)
  - A special study of St. Philip's Church, organization, 1971 (Box 93/206: 12)
  - Bulletins (Box 93/206: 12)
  - Bollinger, misc., report on clergy agreement (Box 93/206: 13)
  - Religious magazines: The Mission Herald, The North Carolina Churchman, Episcopal Church News (Box 93/206: 13)
  - Notices, clippings, printed materials (Box 93/206: 14)
  - Church files: clippings, correspondence, printed materials (Box 93/206: 15)
  - Bulletins, clippings, correspondence, notices, printed materials (Box 93/206: 16)
  - Clippings, notices, printed materials (Box 93/206: 17)
  - Women's auxiliary items (Box 93/206: 17)
  - Bulletins, clippings, church mailings, printed materials (Box 93/206: 18)
  - Register of church services, 1936 January-1955 July, 1972 (Oversize-box 1)
  - Bp. Cheshire's Ordinal (Oversize-box 1)
  - St. Phillip's Guild, 1895-1902 (Oversize-box 1)
  - Congregational meeting, 1951-1961 (Oversize-box 1)
  - Women's Auxiliary financial statements, 1955 July-1958 June (Oversize-box 1)
  - Parish house plans (Oversize-box 1)
  - Duke student center plans (Oversize-box 1)
  - Social survey of the parish (Oversize-box 1)
  - Canonical parish register, 1938 January 1 (Oversize-box 1)
- Accession: 1997-0191
  - The History of St. Philip's Episcopal Church, 1878-1994 (Box 97/0191: 1)
  - Early church history (Box 97/0191: 1)
  - Rectorships: Sidney Stuart Bost (Box 97/0191: 1)
  - Rectorships: David Yates (Box 97/0191: 1)
  - History committee archives (Box 97/0191: 1)
  - History committee archives (Box 97/0191: 2)
  - Rectorships: Clarence Haden (Box 97/0191: 2)
  - Sunday school, 1936-1951 (Box 97/0191: 2)
  - Rectorship: Tom Turney Edwards (Box 97/0191: 2)
  - Rectorship: L. Bartine Sherman (Box 97/0191: 2)
  - Rectorship: L. Bartine Sherman (Box 97/0191: 3)
  - Rectorship: Thomas Eugene Bollinger (Box 97/0191: 3)
  - Rectorship: Thomas Eugene Bollinger (Box 97/0191: 4)
  - Rectorship: C. Thomas Midyette (Box 97/0191: 4)
- Accession: 1998-0020
  A complete file of the extant sermons (1912-1994) collected by Harold Parker, Parish Historian, who compiled the sermons for a book entitled "Sermons from St. Philip's." Also included is corresondence relating to the book and Parker's notes about the sermons. The bulk of the extant sermons consist of 120 sermons written by L. Bartine Sherman (rector 1957-1967).
  - Sermons and correspondence collected by Harold Parker (Box 98/020: 1)
  - Sermons and correspondence collected by Harold Parker (Box 98/020: 2)
- Accession: 1998-0373
  - Search for a rector, 1878-1898 (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Rectorship of Sidney Stuart Bost, 1898-1935 (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Rectorship of David Yates, 1935-1945 (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Rectorship of Clarence R. Hader, Jr., 1945-1951 (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Rectorship of Thomas Turney Edwards, 1951-1956; 2 folders (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Rectorship of Levering Bartine Sherman, 1957-1967 (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Rectorship of Thomas Eugene Bollinger, 1967-1978 (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Rectorship of C. Thomas Midyette, III, 1978-1994 (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Mission to the deaf (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Memorial garden (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Display board photographs (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Vestry minutes microfilm, 1914-1920, 1930-1942 (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Vestry minutes microfilm, 1943-1954, 1959-1966 (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Vestry minutes microfilm, 1958-1992 (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Marriage register and communicants microfilm, 1937-1967 (Box 98/0373: 1)
  - Marriage register and communion register microfilm, 1878-1983 (Box 98/0373: 1)
- Accession: 2000-0175
  This addition further documents church thinking, and also its activities when preparing and publishing a church history. There is an unbound version of St. Philip's published book of seventy sermons as well as the sermons rejected for the book; writing/sermons by Sidney Stuart Bost and others; correspondence, notes and more items related to the preparation of "The History of St. Philip's;" correspondence, photographs, and other items concerning Rev. Midyette's rectorship; and additional sermons.
  - Materials for creating "Sermons from St. Philip's" and "The History of St. Philip's", 1940-1996 (Box 00/0175: 1)
- Accession: 2002-0148
  Addition contains primarily typescript manuscripts and various edited page proofs for Harold T. Parker's "Sermons from St. Philip's." Also includes correspondence regarding the publication of the book and a typescript manuscript, "Chronologies: Harold T. Parker--An Atom in Chaos," that details his life in relation to selected world events.
  - Typescripts and correspondence regarding writing projects of Harold Parker, 2002 (Box 02/148: 1)
  - Typescripts and correspondence regarding writing projects of Harold Parker, 2002 (Box 02/148: 2)